Guide to the NASA-AMES Research Center Publications
Department of Special Collections
NASA-AMES Research Center Publications
Special Collections M1164
NASA-AMES Research Center
4 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Glenn Bugos, 2000.
Historical Note
The NASA-AMES Research Center was founded by NASA in 1941 to conduct experiments in advanced avionics, space vehicle design, robotic exploration of the solar system, and space medicine.
Timeline
1941 AN XB-28 model being prepared for wind tunnel testing in 1941.
1943 Construction proceeds on the 40- by 80-foot wind tunnel in 1943 while a Navy patrol blimp hovers in the background.
1947 First to fly faster than the speed of sound-on October 14, 1947-the XS-1 with then Captain Charles Yeager at the controls.
1949 The Reeves Electronic Analog Computer (REAC), the first electronic computing machine at Ames, was acquired in 1949 to perform control simulation analyses.
1952 H. Julian Allen, Ames second director and the originator of the blunt-body concept used for the first Earth reentry vehicles (Mercury, Gemini, and Apollo).
1961 The famed rocket-powered X-15 aircraft was flown by Ames-Dryden to an altitude of 354,000 feet and 6.7 times the speed of sound.
1963 An early reentry vehicle concept, the M2F2, being tested for low speed landing in the 40x80 wind tunnel.
1965 Pioneer spacecraft begins planetary exploration.
1965-1968 First digital fly-by-wire aircraft control system in the United States.
1972 Artist concept of a Pioneer spacecraft over Jupiter. Both Pioneer 10 and 11 flew past that planet and returned the first close-up pictures.
1975 First flight of Kuiper C-141 Airborne Observatory infrared astronomy platform.
1976 First oblique-wing research aircraft.
1977 The XV-15 tilt-rotor-the efficiency of a fixed-wing, turboprop aircraft with the vertical flight capability of a helicopter-achieves high speed forward flight with vertical takeoff and landing.
1981 The Dryden Flight Research Facility, with numerous runways several miles long on its dry lake beds, is a major Space Shuttle landing site.
1985 Ultraviolt image of Halley's Comet obtained by pioneer venus when the comet was close to perihelion.
1989 Launching of the Galileo probe, designed at Ames. To descend into Jupiter's atmosphere in 1995.
1990 First lauch of the winded, 3-stage rocket Pegasus, from Ames B-52 aircraft. The first time a payload was launched by a privately developed space booster.
1991 One of a chain of sinkholes, whose detection by remote sensing imagery led to discovering the outline of a buried crater rim in the Yucatan Peninsula.
1995 Galileo Probe enters atmosphere of the giant planet Jupiter.
Scope and Content
The collection contains issues of internal publications, such as The Astrogram, and reports on NASA-AMES activities.
Container List
- Astrograms. -- Vol. 1, no. 1-271958 - 1959 Oct. 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Astrograms. -- Vol. 2, no. 1-261959 Oct. 29 - 1960 Oct. 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 3, no. 1-271960 Oct. 27 - 1961 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 4, no. 1-271961 Oct. 26 - 1962 Oct. 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 5, no. 1-271962 Oct. 25 - 1963 Oct. 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 6, no. 1-271963 Oct. 24 - 1964 Oct. 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 7, no. 1-271964 Oct. 21 - 1965 Oct. 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 8, no. 1-251965 Oct. 28 - 1966 Sept. 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 9, no. 1-281966 Oct. 27 - 1967 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 10, no. 1-271967 Dec. 21 - 1968 Oct. 24 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 11, no. 1-281968 Nov. 7 - 1969 Oct. 23 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 12, no. 1-261969 Nov. 6 - 1970 Oct. 22 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 13, no. 1-271970 Oct. 29 - 1971 Oct. 14 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 14, no. 1-311971 Oct. 28 - 1972 Oct. 12 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 15, no. 1-281972 Oct. 26 - 1973 Oct. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 16, no. 1-291973 Oct. 25 - 1974 Oct. 21 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 17, no. 1-281974 Oct. 24 - 1975 Sept. 11 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 18, no. 1-271975 Oct. 9 - 1976 Oct. 7 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 19, no. 1-291976 Oct. 21 - 1977 Nov. 3 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 20, no. 1-261977 Nov. 17 - 1978 Oct. 16 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 23, no. 1-251980 Oct. 17 - 1981 Sept. 18 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 24, no. 1-271981 Oct. 2 - 1982 Sept. 24 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 25, no. 1-271982 Oct. 1 - 1983 Sept. 30 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 26, no. 1-261983 Oct. 14 - 1984 Sept. 27 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 27, no. 1-271984 Oct. 11 - 1985 Sept. 26 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 28, no. 1-271985 Oct. 10 - 1986 Sept. 25 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 29, no. 1-251986 Oct. 9 - 1987 Sept. 18 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 30, no. 1-17, 19-271987 Oct. 1 - 1988 Sept. 23 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 31, no. 1-261988 Oct. 7 - 1989 Sept. 22 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 32, no. 12, 4-281989 Oct. 6 - 1990 Oct. 12 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 33, no. 1-261990 Oct. 26 - 1991 Sept. 27 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Astrogram. -- Vol. 34, no. 1-161991 Oct. 11 - 1992 May 8 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Astrogram.1992 May 22 - 1992 Dec. 18 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Astrogram.1993 Jan. 8 - Dec. 10 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Astrogram.1994 Jan. 7 - Dec. 23 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Astrogram.1995 Jan. 27 - Dec. 15 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Astrogram.1996 Jan. 12 - Dec. 13 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Astrogram.1997 Jan. 10 - Dec. 12 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Astrogram.1998 Jan. 9 - Dec. 11 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Astrogram.1999 Jan. 15 - Dec. 20 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Astrogram.2000 Jan. 24 - June 26 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Aerospace systems directorate: goals and activities.1987 June (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Agenda for tomorrow.1988 Dec. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Ames Research facilities summary.1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Art of excellence at Ames Research Center.1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Automation sciences research facility.n.d. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Contributions of Ames' research scientists to the aerospace literature in 1969.1969 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Contributions of Ames' research scientists to the aerospace literature in 1970.1970 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Contributions of Ames' research scientists to the aerospace literature in 1971.1971 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Cultural climate & practices plan.1993 March 10 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Edwards Facility.1987 Nov. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Fourth national reunion of NACA.1988 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Future begins here.n.d. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Highlights of Ames Research Center's first 50 years, 1939-1989.n.d. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Iniation of construction: 80 x 120 foot wind tunnel.1978 November 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  2 copies.
- NASA superstars of science.1978 November 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Research facilities handbook.1982 June (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Space flight of Astronaut Shepard and the Freedom Seven.1961 May 5 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Space Station Freedom: dawn of a new era.n.d. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Strategic plan.1994 May (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Women at work in NASA.1979 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Bugos, Glenn. Atmosphere of Freedom: sixty years at the NASA Ames Research Center. -- (NASA History Series). -- Washington, D.C.: NASA History Office, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Numerical aerodynamic simulation.n.d. (Box 7)
- LIFE Magazine.1964 Oct. 2 (Box 7)
  Contains article on NASA.